<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: DevOps | TheLadders Engineering Stories]]></title>
  <link href="http://dev.theladders.com/categories/devops/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://dev.theladders.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-04-27T10:48:17-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://dev.theladders.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[TheLadders Engineering]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[MMR is not Measles, Mumps, and Rubella]]></title>
    <link href="http://dev.theladders.com/2015/01/not-measles/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-22T15:58:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://dev.theladders.com/2015/01/not-measles</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><blockquote><p>Communication Breakdown, It&rsquo;s always the same,<br/>I&rsquo;m having a nervous breakdown, Drive me insane!</p><footer><strong>&mdash;Led Zeppelin</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>tl;dr &mdash; Use this <a href="http://github.com/TheLadders/monitor-ds-replication">plugin</a> to monitor 389 Directory Server replication</p>

<p>We&rsquo;ve been bitten in the past when the multi-master replication between our authentication servers stops functioning properly and we don&rsquo;t find out about it immediately.  This usually manifests itself as users complaining that they&rsquo;re intermittently unable to authenticate against certain services, which results in a bunch of troubleshooting effort only to discover that the real problem is the user not existing on all IPA servers.</p>

<p>We use <a href="http://freeipa.org">freeIPA</a> internally as our centralized user management system.  freeIPA combines several standard open source components to provide an &ldquo;integrated security information management solution&rdquo;.  These components include <a href="http://directory.fedoraproject.org/">389 Directory Server</a>, <a href="http://k5wiki.kerberos.org/wiki/Main_Page">MIT Kerberos</a>, <a href="http://www.ntp.org">NTP</a>, <a href="http://fedorahosted.org/bind-dyndb-ldap/">DNS</a>, <a href="http://pki.fedoraproject.org/">Dogtag certificate system</a>, <a href="http://fedorahosted.org/sssd/">SSSD</a> as well as several others.  In the absence of custom configuration, freeIPA utilizes two instances of 389 Directory Server &ndash; one for traditional directory information on the standard port 389, and one for <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public_key_infrastructure">PKI/CA</a> on port 7389.  389 Directory Server&rsquo;s multi-master replication (MMR) support ensures that directory and certificate data is available from any node in the cluster.</p>

<p>To prevent this unfortunate scenario in the future, we developed a simple <a href="http://www.nagios.org">nagios</a>/<a href="http://www.icinga.org">icinga</a> plugin to assess replication health within the 389 Directory Server cluster.  Fortunately, information including structure of the cluster and status of replication is stored within the LDAP schema itself.  In developing the plugin, we hoped to avoid storing any authentication details in the plugin or the nagios/icinga configuration.  This required enabling anonymous read-only querying of the replication agreement data.  Daniel James Scott&rsquo;s <a href="http://danieljamesscott.org/11-articles/application-guides/26-freeipa-replication-monitoring.html">blog post</a> provided very clear instructions for enabling anonymous read/search/compare access to the replication agreements.  Our <a href="http://github.com/TheLadders/monitor-ds-replication">plugin</a> uses the <a href="http://rubygems.org/gems/net-ldap">Net::LDAP</a> Ruby gem to interact with a 389 Directory Server instance to discover all of the downstream replicas and their respective status.  We query the ldap server with base <code>cn=config</code> and filter on <code>(objectclass=nsds5replicationagreement)</code>.  The equivalent command line query is:
<code>
ldapsearch -x -h openldap_server.example.com -b cn=config '(objectclass=nsds5replicationagreement)'
</code>
This yields data similar to:</p>

<p>```</p>

<h1>extended LDIF</h1>

<p>#</p>

<h1>LDAPv3</h1>

<h1>base &lt;cn=config> with scope subtree</h1>

<h1>filter: (objectclass=nsds5replicationagreement)</h1>

<h1>requesting: ALL</h1>

<p>#</p>

<h1>meToipa-1.example.com, replica, dc\3Dexample\2Cdc\3com, mapping tree, config</h1>

<p>dn: cn=meToipa-1.example.com,cn=replica,cn=dc\3Dexample\2Cdc\3Dcom,cn=mapping tree,cn=config
cn: meToipa-1.example.com
objectClass: nsds5replicationagreement
objectClass: top
nsDS5ReplicaTransportInfo: LDAP
description: me to ipa-1.example.com
nsDS5ReplicaRoot: dc=example,dc=com
nsDS5ReplicaHost: ipa-1.example.com
nsds5replicaTimeout: 120
nsDS5ReplicaPort: 389
nsDS5ReplicatedAttributeList: (objectclass=<em>) $ EXCLUDE memberof idnssoaserialentryusn krblastsuccessfulauth krblastfailedauth krbloginfailedcount
nsDS5ReplicaBindMethod: SASL/GSSAPI
nsDS5ReplicatedAttributeListTotal: (objectclass=</em>) $ EXCLUDE entryusn krblastsuccessfulauth krblastfailedauth krbloginfailedcount
nsds5replicareapactive: 0
nsds5replicaLastUpdateStart: 20150121214458Z
nsds5replicaLastUpdateEnd: 20150121214501Z
nsds5replicaChangesSentSinceStartup:: MTM6MjAwMzUxNy8wIDY6NC8wIDE0OjQ0MjkvMCA=
nsds5replicaLastUpdateStatus: 1 Can&rsquo;t acquire busy replica
nsds5replicaUpdateInProgress: FALSE
nsds5replicaLastInitStart: 0
nsds5replicaLastInitEnd: 0</p>

<h1>meToipa-2.example.com, replica, dc\3Dexample\2Cdc\3Dcom, mapping tree, config</h1>

<p>dn: cn=meToipa-2.example.com,cn=replica,cn=dc\3Dexample\2Cdc\3Dcom,cn=mapping tree,cn=config
cn: meToipa-2.example.com
objectClass: nsds5replicationagreement
objectClass: top
nsDS5ReplicaTransportInfo: LDAP
description: me to ipa-2.example.com
nsDS5ReplicaRoot: dc=example,dc=com
nsDS5ReplicaHost: ipa-2.example.com
nsds5replicaTimeout: 120
nsDS5ReplicaPort: 389
nsDS5ReplicatedAttributeList: (objectclass=<em>) $ EXCLUDE memberof idnssoaserialentryusn krblastsuccessfulauth krblastfailedauth krbloginfailedcount
nsDS5ReplicaBindMethod: SASL/GSSAPI
nsDS5ReplicatedAttributeListTotal: (objectclass=</em>) $ EXCLUDE entryusn krblastsuccessfulauth krblastfailedauth krbloginfailedcount
nsds5replicareapactive: 0
nsds5replicaLastUpdateStart: 20150121214628Z
nsds5replicaLastUpdateEnd: 0
nsds5replicaChangesSentSinceStartup:: Njo0MzEyLzAgMTM6NDAzMjMzOS8wIA==
nsds5replicaLastUpdateStatus: 0 Replica acquired successfully: Incremental update started
nsds5replicaUpdateInProgress: TRUE
nsds5replicaLastInitStart: 20141215154802Z
nsds5replicaLastInitEnd: 20141215154807Z
nsds5replicaLastInitStatus: 0 Total update succeeded</p>

<h1>search result</h1>

<p>search: 2
result: 0 Success</p>

<h1>numResponses: 3</h1>

<h1>numEntries: 2</h1>

<p>```</p>

<p>We&rsquo;re primarily concerned with how far in the past each replica successfully performed an update.  As you can see from the output above, the replication agreement with ipa-2.example.com is in the middle of an incremental update and shows a last update end of <code>0</code>.  This does not necessarily mean that replication is broken.  For better or worse, when the server begins an update, it clears the last end time.  To avoid constantly alerting when we&rsquo;re unable to retrieve meaningful replication data, the plugin maintains a state file that tracks the last valid update completion time and how many times a check has resulted in a last update completion of <code>0</code>.  The number of successive zero responses and acceptable number of minutes since last successful update completion are configurable parameters with the ability to set distinct warning and critical thresholds.</p>

<p>Since putting this monitoring in place, we&rsquo;ve moved to newer freeIPA servers using replication to seamlessly migrate data from the old servers to the new.  This plugin has already served to identify a breakdown in our replication that was easily remedied because the nodes had not yet significantly diverged.  Other aspects of the health and performance of the IPA cluster are available via SNMP.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pipes, Tubes, and Email]]></title>
    <link href="http://dev.theladders.com/2014/11/pipes-tubes-and-email/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-18T09:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://dev.theladders.com/2014/11/pipes-tubes-and-email</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><blockquote><p>It&rsquo;s not a big truck.  It&rsquo;s a series of tubes.  And if you don&rsquo;t understand, those tubes can be filled and if they are filled, when you put your message in, it gets in line and it&rsquo;s going to be delayed.</p><footer><strong>&mdash;US Senator Ted Stevens (R-Alaska)</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<h2>Plumbing 101</h2>

<p>Sending email is a major part of our business.  Over the years, TheLadders has moved through several iterations of getting emails out to our millions of job seekers and recruiters.  We&rsquo;ve both built in-house solutions and utilized <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Email_service_provider_(marketing)">Email Service Providers (ESPs)</a>.</p>

<p>Recently, we transitioned onto a new ESP, <a href="http://sendgrid.com">SendGrid</a>.  SendGrid offers us the choice of handing off email via their <a href="https://sendgrid.com/docs/API_Reference/Web_API/index.html">HTTP</a> or <a href="https://sendgrid.com/docs/API_Reference/SMTP_API/index.html">SMTP</a> APIs.  We selected <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simple_Mail_Transfer_Protocol">SMTP</a> as our transport mechanism because it allows us the luxury of inserting a layer in our infrastructure to handle queueing and resilience of mail transport before handing messages across to the ESP.  We are also able to achieve higher overall throughput with SMTP than would be possible with the HTTP API.  We&rsquo;re using <a href="http://www.postfix.org">Postfix</a> as our mail transport agent because of its scalability properties, the flexibility of its configuration options and our team&rsquo;s familiarity with running and maintaining the application.</p>

<p>To ensure that our subscribers receive the emails we send them, we divide the different types of messages across multiple sub-user accounts at SendGrid.  This spreads our outbound email across different source IPs depending on the chosen sub-user account and allows us to control the reputation of each IP group.  In addition to the usual challenges that go along with deploying any new infrastructure &mdash; monitor it, scale it, make it highly available &mdash; SendGrid&rsquo;s use of SMTP authentication credentials to determine which sub-user account will handle the sending of a particular message created a new and interesting problem to solve.  How could we allow our application to instruct Postfix which sub-user account to use without building a Postfix cluster for each sub-user account?  Moreover, how could we make that process invisible to our end recipient?</p>

<h2>Don&rsquo;t Clog the Tubes!</h2>

<p>The majority of our email traffic is created by various <a href="/categories/storm/">Storm</a> topologies crunching through our data.  Storm provides the ability to parallelize each step in the process, resulting in fairly rapid generation of email traffic.  We utilize our F5 load balancers in front of a pool of Postfix servers to make our mail transport layer both fault-tolerant and scalable.  During our larger sends, we prefer messages to be sent out with minimal queueing.  We&rsquo;ve found after tuning that we can sustain roughly 7000 messages per second through a single Postfix server before messages begin to queue.  We can easily scale out to additional Postfix servers behind the load balancer to increase our total throughput.</p>

<p><img class="center medium" src="/images/pipes-tubes-and-email/animated_email_flow.gif"></p>

<h2>Pick a Tube</h2>

<p>Postfix provides the <a href="http://www.postfix.org/postconf.5.html#smtp_sasl_password_maps">SASL Password Map</a> mechanism to look up SMTP credentials based on remote hostname or domain.  When coupled with <a href="http://www.postfix.org/postconf.5.html#smtp_sender_dependent_authentication">Sender-dependent Authentication</a>, that lookup can be performed based on the sender address.  We leveraged this combination of options along with <a href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc5233#page-2">plus-sign subaddressing</a> to encode the sub-user account in the message&rsquo;s source address, so an email from <code>user@example.com</code> would actually be sent from <code>user+account@example.com</code>.</p>

<p>We utilize a regular expression map for the password selection that matches the subaddress portion of the sender address and returns the appropriate sub-user account credentials to postfix, with a default for messages that come through without a subaddress.</p>

<p><code>plain SASL Password Map
/^.*\+user1@example.com$/   user1:password1
/^.*\+user2@example.com$/   user2:password2
/^.*$/                      defaultuser:defaultpassword
</code></p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper center medium'><img class='caption' src='/images/pipes-tubes-and-email/pick-a-tube.jpg' width='' height='' alt='<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/biscuitsmlp/2431615179">Photo</a> by <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/biscuitsmlp/">smlp.co.uk</a> / <a href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">CC BY 2.0</a>' title='<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/biscuitsmlp/2431615179">Photo</a> by <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/biscuitsmlp/">smlp.co.uk</a> / <a href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">CC BY 2.0</a>'><span class='caption-text'><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/biscuitsmlp/2431615179">Photo</a> by <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/biscuitsmlp/">smlp.co.uk</a> / <a href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">CC BY 2.0</a></span></span></p>

<h2>Keep Your Tubes Straight</h2>

<p>While our solution works great for allowing our applications to properly route messages to the correct sub-user account, it doesn&rsquo;t necessarily provide the best customer facing appearance.  Our customers don&rsquo;t care what ESP we use, how we perform our sub-user account selection, or which sub-user account sourced their email.  Furthermore, a sudden change in source email address could cause our messages to be filtered incorrectly on the recipient side.  Perhaps a customer has a filter in place to always drop our messages into a specific folder for them to read later.  Maybe they have a strict policy stating that only mail from known addresses will end up in their inbox.  We periodically have to adjust how our outbound email is processed and we have to make those changes as transparent as possible for our customers.  To that end, we are also utilizing Postfix&rsquo;s address rewriting capabilities to ensure that our email source addresses remain consistent.</p>

<p>Postfix provides several opportunities and methods to transform email envelope information <a href="http://www.postfix.org/ADDRESS_REWRITING_README.html">for a variety of purposes</a>.  Our requirement was to transform messages sent from <code>user+account@example.com</code> so that the customer sees the message sourced from <code>user@example.com</code>.  <a href="http://www.postfix.org/postconf.5.html#sender_canonical_maps">Sender canonical maps</a> initially seemed like the ideal solution to this problem.  It worked perfectly to transform the sender address as desired however, the transformation occurred so early in the process that addresses were being rewritten before the subaccount selection was performed.  We finally settled on <a href="http://www.postfix.org/postconf.5.html#smtp_generic_maps">SMTP generic maps</a> as the correct solution since it performs its transformation when mail leaves the machine via SMTP, after all other processing has taken place.  We again use a regular expression to strip the subaccount information from source addresses.</p>

<p><code>plain SMTP Generic Map
/^(.*)\+(.*)@(.*)$/ ${1}@${3}
</code></p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper center medium'><img class='caption' src='/images/pipes-tubes-and-email/the-internet.jpg' width='' height='' alt='<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/wheresmysocks/205710716">Photo</a> by <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/wheresmysocks/">Kendrick Erickson</a> / <a href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">CC BY 2.0</a>' title='<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/wheresmysocks/205710716">Photo</a> by <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/wheresmysocks/">Kendrick Erickson</a> / <a href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">CC BY 2.0</a>'><span class='caption-text'><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/wheresmysocks/205710716">Photo</a> by <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/wheresmysocks/">Kendrick Erickson</a> / <a href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">CC BY 2.0</a></span></span></p>

<h2>Pipes or Tubes</h2>

<p>Pulling it all together with the <a href="https://sendgrid.com/docs/Integrate/Mail_Servers/postfix.html">recommended Postfix config</a> from SendGrid, results in <code>/etc/postfix/main.cf</code> containing:</p>

<p><code>plain main.cf
smtp_sasl_auth_enable = yes
smtp_sender_dependent_authentication = yes
smtp_sasl_password_maps = pcre:/path/to/sasl_password_map
smtp_generic_maps = pcre:/path/to/smtp_generic_map
smtp_sasl_security_options = noanonymous
smtp_tls_security_level = encrypt
header_size_limit = 4096000
</code></p>

<p>Find this post interesting? Join the discussion over on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=8623846">Hacker News</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Thunder and Lightning]]></title>
    <link href="http://dev.theladders.com/2014/07/thunder-and-lightning/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-23T09:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://dev.theladders.com/2014/07/thunder-and-lightning</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><blockquote><p>The simplest of explanations is more likely to be correct than any other.</p><footer><strong>&mdash;Occam&rsquo;s Razor</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<h2>Braving the Storm</h2>

<p>At TheLadders, we operate a fully virtualized environment consisting of slightly less than a thousand virtual machines across our Development, QA, and Production environments.  We manage these systems with <a href="http://puppetlabs.com">Puppet</a> and <a href="http://theforeman.org">Foreman</a>, which enables us to rapidly deploy new systems when necessary, as well as maintain our systems predictably throughout their lifecycles.</p>

<p>One of the tools we <a href="http://dev.theladders.com/categories/storm/">rely on heavily</a> is <a href="https://storm.incubator.apache.org">Storm</a>, a distributed, real-time computation system.  Storm provides us with a framework that we use to constantly crunch data about the millions of job seekers and jobs in our environment.  This enables us to provide our job seekers with relevant information about the best jobs available to them at any given time.  When we build new Storm nodes, Puppet takes a very minimal OS install, lays down our standard configuration, then installs Storm, starts the Storm process and ensures it will start after reboot.</p>

<h2>Dark Skies Ahead</h2>

<p>We operate several Storm clusters across QA and Production spanning Storm versions 0.8 and 0.9.  Over the past several months, we&rsquo;ve experienced intermittent issues within the clusters where individual nodes stopped behaving properly.  The issues occur more frequently in our Production environment, which we attribute to the orders of magnitude higher volumes of traffic traversing Production.  We&rsquo;ve also seen this particular issue in both our 0.8 and 0.9 clusters.  Until recently, the problem has occurred so infrequently that it was much quicker and easier to shut down and rebuild the problem nodes than invest significant time nailing down the root cause.</p>

<p>Last month, we rebuilt our 0.9 Production cluster from the ground up and immediately began seeing topologies fail to start on multiple workers.  The issue was clouded by the fact that we saw several different errors occurring, including too many files open, DNS resolution failures, Java class not found errors, heartbeat file not found, etc.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper center medium'><img class='caption' src='/images/thunder-and-lightning/stormy-city.jpg' width='' height='' alt='<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/29311691@N05/7653430352">Photo</a> by <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/29311691@N05/">H.L.I.T.</a> / <a href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">CC BY 2.0</a>' title='<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/29311691@N05/7653430352">Photo</a> by <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/29311691@N05/">H.L.I.T.</a> / <a href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">CC BY 2.0</a>'><span class='caption-text'><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/29311691@N05/7653430352">Photo</a> by <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/29311691@N05/">H.L.I.T.</a> / <a href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">CC BY 2.0</a></span></span></p>

<h2>When it Rains, it Pours</h2>

<p>Since we were seeing multiple errors occurring without any obviously predictable pattern, we started the investigation by trying to reproduce or verify the individual errors on the nodes where we saw the issues in the Nimbus interface.  Despite complaints from Storm of DNS resolution issues, we were unable to find any issues with our DNS system or name resolution on any of the nodes in the cluster, even when performing many lookups in rapid succession.</p>

<p>After eliminating DNS as a root cause, we surmised that the real problem was limits on open file handles and that the other errors &mdash; Java class not found, heartbeat file not found and DNS resolution failure &mdash; were just different manifestations of the process’ inability to open a file handle or socket.  One change that Puppet makes to our systems is to increase the open file handle limits for the storm user/process from the default of 1024 to 256k.  We do this by setting the <code>nofile</code> option in <code>/etc/security/limits.conf</code>.  We verified on every host that the Storm user had properly set file handle limits.  Observing the workers when they were experiencing the issue proved difficult because Storm dynamically assigns workers to nodes at process startup and processes are not sticky.  This means that in our situation, where processes were starting and dying very quickly, it was extremely challenging to be logged into the host watching the process and gathering useful data in the few seconds between startup and death.  One approach to avoid this problem was to shut down workers to eliminate unused worker slots, thus limiting the potential destinations for new processes.  After a prolonged struggle with observing a process as it died, we were finally able to see that the worker process itself was limited to the default 1024 file handles.  We confirmed this suspicion by watching <code>/proc/&lt;PID&gt;/limits</code> to confirm that all Storm related processes were limited to 1024 open file handles on the affected hosts.</p>

<h2>Every Cloud has a Silver Lining</h2>

<p>Now that we had observed a worker process with a 1024 open file handle limit, we moved on to determining how this could happen and why it seemed to occur only on certain nodes.  We noted that rebooting a host did not resolve the issue and further that rebooting a working node caused it to cease functioning properly.  After quite a bit of experimentation, we found that manually restarting the Storm supervisor on an affected host allowed the node to function properly again, at least until the next reboot.</p>

<p>We recently altered our new machine deployment to reboot the host between running Puppet and putting the machine in service.  Whereas previously the Storm supervisor would be started by Puppet and function normally, the supervisor is now being started by init on boot.</p>

<p>We ultimately determined that the root cause of this issue is that processes started by init don&rsquo;t go through pam, so limits set in <code>/etc/security/limits.conf</code>, which is utilized by <code>pam_limits.so</code>, are not applied to processes started on boot.</p>

<p>We chose to solve this issue by following the RHEL convention of configuration in /etc/sysconfig and modifying the storm supervisor init script to load <code>/etc/sysconfig/storm</code> if it exists.  Our <code>/etc/sysconfig/storm</code> contains a single line for the time being, increasing the <code>nofile</code> limit to 256k.  This method provides us with the flexibility to augment the configuration in the future with minimal impact.</p>

<p>Once Puppet deployed this change to our entire environment, we verified via <code>/proc/&lt;PID&gt;/limits</code> that the Storm supervisors had picked up the changes both when started by hand/Puppet and when started on boot.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
