<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Scaling | TheLadders Engineering Stories]]></title>
  <link href="http://dev.theladders.com/categories/scaling/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://dev.theladders.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-24T14:37:34-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://dev.theladders.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[TheLadders Engineering]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Denormalize the Datas for Great Good]]></title>
    <link href="http://dev.theladders.com/2013/07/denormalize-the-datas-for-great-good/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-08T16:02:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://dev.theladders.com/2013/07/denormalize-the-datas-for-great-good</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><blockquote><p>Normal is not something to aspire to, it&rsquo;s something to get away from.</p><footer><strong>&mdash;Jodie Foster</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<h2>Scout reads go slow</h2>

<p>A few weeks ago, as we were about to launch our <a href="http://app.appsflyer.com/id654867487?pid=TLC_organic">iPhone app</a>, we discovered that one of its core features, Scout, frequently took seconds to render.</p>

<center>
<span class='caption-wrapper small'><img class='caption' src='/images/denormalize-the-datas-for-great-good/scout-screenshot.png' width='' height='' alt='Scout' title='Scout'><span class='caption-text'>Scout</span></span>
</center>


<p>For a little background as to what Scout is, at TheLadders our mission is to find the right person for the right job. One of the ways we strive to deliver on that promise is to provide jobseekers information about jobs they’ll find nowhere else. Serving that mission is Scout, which in a nutshell allows jobseekers to view anonymized information about applicants who have applied to the job they are viewing. Salary, education, career history: we present a lot of useful information to jobseekers about their competition for any given job.</p>

<p>Over time, some attractive jobs accumulate on the order of 30 to 60 applicants, yielding response times of over 1 second (due to multiple synchronous requests, done serially, just to serve <em>one</em> Scout view request).  In cases of higher load, sometimes request times take well over that.</p>

<center>
<span class='caption-wrapper small'><img class='caption' src='/images/denormalize-the-datas-for-great-good/scout-screenshot-many-applies.png' width='' height='' alt='Scout view of a job with many applicants' title='Scout view of a job with many applicants'><span class='caption-text'>Scout view of a job with many applicants</span></span>
</center>


<p>That brings Scout into unusably slow country, as the Graphite chart below indicates:</p>

<center>
<span class='caption-wrapper medium'><img class='caption' src='/images/denormalize-the-datas-for-great-good/before-graphite.png' width='' height='' alt='95th percentile of response times for Scout in seconds' title='95th percentile of response times for Scout in seconds'><span class='caption-text'>95th percentile of response times for Scout in seconds</span></span>
</center>


<p>The graph shows the time it takes to form a response to a view-job request issued by our iPhone app. It’s the 95th percentile, which means that 5% of requests had times of the lines in the graph or higher for any given date.  One in twenty requests took this long or longer. There are many lines because we have a horizontally scalable architecture, so there are many backend app nodes.</p>

<p>We managed to bring those seconds down to milliseconds, with about a 1000x decrease in times of high load.  Below I’ll describe the changes in our architecture that enabled us to make such a huge improvement.</p>

<hr />

<h2>Architecture</h2>

<p>In its initial implementation, Scout’s applicant information was gathered and assembled on the fly for each and every request. Driving the iPhone app, we have a backend app server, which is essentially just a number of RESTful endpoints against which our iPhone app issues requests.  Below is a quick rundown of the architecture before I trace a request through our architecture.</p>

<center>
<span class='caption-wrapper medium'><img class='caption' src='/images/denormalize-the-datas-for-great-good/front-end-orchestration.png' width='' height='' alt='iPhone app talks to the backend app server' title='iPhone app talks to the backend app server'><span class='caption-text'>iPhone app talks to the backend app server</span></span>
</center>


<p>Below this backend server there are a number of RESTful entity servers with which the app server is interacting via HTTP.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper center medium'><img class='caption' src='/images/denormalize-the-datas-for-great-good/front-end-orchestration-entity.png' width='' height='' alt='Backend app server relies on entity servers' title='Backend app server relies on entity servers'><span class='caption-text'>Backend app server relies on entity servers</span></span></p>

<p>These entity servers in turn query each other and the canonical data store, in our case Clustrix, and that’s that.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper center medium'><img class='caption' src='/images/denormalize-the-datas-for-great-good/front-end-orchestration-entity-clustrix.png' width='' height='' alt='Entity servers query the db' title='Entity servers query the db'><span class='caption-text'>Entity servers query the db</span></span></p>

<p>So when a user of our iPhone app taps on a job, a request is sent to the backend app server&hellip;</p>

<p><img class="center medium" src="/images/denormalize-the-datas-for-great-good/mobile-orchestration-request.png" title="iPhone app makes a request" ></p>

<p>&hellip;which then issues a request to our job application service for all job applications for that job. The response contains a number of links to the where those job applications may be retrieved.</p>

<p><img class="center medium" src="/images/denormalize-the-datas-for-great-good/mobile-orchestration-service-request.png" title="backend server queries the job application service for all applications to a job" ></p>

<p>The backend server iterates over those links, requesting the job applications themselves one at a time. Just as before, adhering to hypermedia design, the response contains a link to the jobseeker who applied to the job. For your sanity, I’ve simplified the response to contain only the job seeker link:</p>

<p><img class="center medium" src="/images/denormalize-the-datas-for-great-good/mobile-orchestration-service-request2.png" title="backend retrieves each application" ></p>

<p>Finally with that result set, the orchestration service then issues a number of requests to the job seeker service for information about the job seekers who have applied to the job being viewed.  In its initial implementation all of the requests were synchronous and in series as I mentioned earlier. We eventually parallelized them, as you can see in the Graphite chart where the big spikes left diminish towards the right.</p>

<p><img class="center medium" src="/images/denormalize-the-datas-for-great-good/mobile-orchestration-service-request3.png" title="backend retrieves each application" ></p>

<p>The iPhone app backend server then extracts the relevant information from those job seekers’ profiles, and returns them as a JSON array of applicants to the mobile app.</p>

<p><img class="center medium" src="/images/denormalize-the-datas-for-great-good/mobile-orchestration-response.png" title="backend retrieves each application" ></p>

<p>That is not just a lot of words and diagrams, that is a lot of work!</p>

<p>The workflow includes multiple objects serializing and deserializing, HTTP transfers, hitting the canonical store etc. Why does each request need to assemble this data itself? Why bother hitting the database? Is there an alternative? It seems like a natural fit for a document-oriented database, as the data we are passing back to the client is just a JSON object containing an array of applicants.  We could stand a <a href="http://dev.theladders.com/2013/05/varnish-in-five-acts/">Varnish cache</a> in front of the Scout endpoints on the orchestration service, but then we’d be trading freshness for speed. On the platform team we like to deliver data fast and fresh (and furious).</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/denormalize-the-datas-for-great-good/tokyo-drift-o.gif" title="how we roll at the Democratic Republic of Platformia" ></p>

<hr />

<h2>Scout reads go fast</h2>

<p>Principal Architect <a href="http://twitter.com/SeanTAllen">Sean T Allen</a> set <a href="http://twitter.com/casio_juarez">Andy Turley</a> and me to improving Scout’s performance. The architecture is surprisingly simple: stick the data in <a href="http://www.couchbase.com/">Couchbase</a> and have the iPhone app backend query that instead. How would we keep this data up-to-date? The first step is to have the job application entity service emit a RabbitMQ event when it receives an application from a job seeker to a particular job (a PUT returning a 201).  On the other end of that message queue there is a  <a href="http://dev.theladders.com/2013/03/riders-on-the-storm-take-a-long-holiday-let-your-children-play/">Storm</a> topology that should listen for that message. The RabbitMQ message would be the entry point into the spout.</p>

<p>The message contains a link to the job seeker who applied to the job, as well as the ID for the job to which she applied.   The message isn’t actually encoded as JSON and transmitted over the wire, but for clarity I’ve displayed the RabbitMQ message as JSON.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/denormalize-the-datas-for-great-good/rabbitmq-storm.png" title="RabbitMQ passes along a job-application message to a listening Storm topology" ></p>

<p>The second step, after having received the RabbitMQ message, fetches the job seeker profile from the jobseeker service, and passes that information to the next step.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/denormalize-the-datas-for-great-good/rabbitmq-storm-jobseeker.png" title="The Storm topology extracts the job seeker link from the messages and retrieves information about the job seeker who just applied to the job." ></p>

<p>This third step is responsible for persisting the applicant information to a Couchbase bucket. It uses the job ID as the key, and it does a create or update operation on the document corresponding to that key depending on whether there are applicants already in the bucket for that job.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/denormalize-the-datas-for-great-good/rabbitmq-storm-couchbase.png" title="The final step is that the topology persists the relevant job" ></p>

<p>That last diagram is a bit of a simplification. Although Couchbase is &ldquo;JSON-aware&rdquo;, it lacks the ability to perform certain operations on the JSON documents it stores.  For example, if the document being stored is an Array, and the client&rsquo;s append method is called, we hoped that Couchbase would add that element to the end of the Array. Instead, it&rsquo;s just a blind String.append, resulting in an invalid JSON document. As a result, we had to implement our own append operation by reading the document (if it exists), adding an item to a list if it’s not already there, and then writing the document.  So it’s more like two operations than one.</p>

<p><em>Now</em> when TheLadders mobile service gets a request for Scout information for a job, all it does is a lookup in Couchbase with that job ID and returns the applicants associated with that key.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/denormalize-the-datas-for-great-good/mobile-orchestration-couchbase.png" title="iPhone issues a request for Scout information, backend just retrieves it from couchbase" ></p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper center'><img class='caption' src='/images/denormalize-the-datas-for-great-good/before-couchbase-after-no-lines.png' width='' height='' alt='95th percentile response time for Scout data, before and after moving to the read view' title='95th percentile response time for Scout data, before and after moving to the read view'><span class='caption-text'>95th percentile response time for Scout data, before and after moving to the read view</span></span></p>

<p>Dramatically faster, even at the 95th percentile.</p>

<hr />

<p>SOA is no panacea. There are many instances where querying a number of backend servers to assemble and aggregate data returned from a database simply doesn&rsquo;t make sense. In those cases, you may do well to denormalize that data and put it in a store that&rsquo;s more efficient for retrieval.</p>

<p>If you find this post interesting, join the dicussion over on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=6015123">Hacker News</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Varnish in Five Acts]]></title>
    <link href="http://dev.theladders.com/2013/05/varnish-in-five-acts/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-03T13:21:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://dev.theladders.com/2013/05/varnish-in-five-acts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><blockquote><p>“Take a load off Annie. Take a load for free. Take a load off Annie. And you put the load right on me.” &mdash; Robbie Robertson</p></blockquote></p>

<h2>Act I: The Players</h2>

<p>At TheLadders, we have a number of entity services that clients access via HTTP. Some examples are the job service, the job application service and the topic of this post: the job seeker service. Each service manages the lifecycle of a core entity in our domain. On each request, the service gathers data from multiple data sources to build a complete entity and then serializes that entity to JSON. This is done for every request and is incredibly wasteful when you consider that most of these entities don’t change that often. This was a major bottleneck in our infrastructure. In the case of the job seeker service, the same entity can be requested multiple times per request from our consumer website.</p>

<p>All this repeated, unnecessary entity object assembly and JSON serialization created scaling problems. Making matters worse, we periodically have batch processes that can increase service load by an order of magnitude. Caching is an easy win here. The question is how.</p>

<p>Initial attempts to cache these entities were done inside the service JVMs, using familiar and popular JVM based caches like EHcache and calls out to memcache. Unfortunately, this left us operating at JVM speeds and the caches were competing with the service logic for memory and threads.</p>

<p>In addition, our service code was muddled with messy caching logic.  Making the code harder to reuse, and more annoyingly, changes just affecting caching forced us to re-release the entire service.  We didn’t like this mixing of concerns.</p>

<p>We thought we could do better if we used external read through caches. It&rsquo;s easy to slide them between existing clients and services. With caching outside the service, it get released only when their logic changes not because we’re tuning caching.</p>

<p>For reasons too numerous to cover in this post we chose <a href="https://www.varnish-cache.org/about">Varnish</a> as our read through cache.</p>

<hr />

<h2>Act II: The Architecture</h2>

<p>When we introduced Varnish to our architecture, we wanted to make sure we were not adding a single point of failure. Simply put, if the cache layer goes down, our infrastructure should continue running. Performance might be degraded, but we should continue to be able to serve content to clients.</p>

<p>The diagram below shows a typical setup. In a normal scenario, a client accesses Varnish via a load balancer. Varnish in turn farms out the work in round robin fashion to one of four job seeker service nodes. Should Varnish become unavailable, the load balancer stops sending traffic to Varnish and reroutes it to the four job seeker service nodes.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/varnish-in-five-acts/varnish-flow.png"></p>

<p>Of all our entity services, the job seeker services carries the highest median load. The graph below is the 1 minute request rate on 4 jobseeker service nodes over the 36 hour period before and after Varnish was turned on.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/varnish-in-five-acts/before-after.png"></p>

<hr />

<h2>Act III: Cache Invalidation</h2>

<p>Cache invalidation is one of the 2 hard problems in computer science along with naming things and off by one errors.</p>

<p>We cache job seeker entity representations until some point in the “far future”, which is great until something about that job seeker changes, then we must invalidate the cached entry. So, how do we do that?</p>

<p>Two ways.</p>

<h3>Via Header:</h3>

<p>All requests that change the state of a job seeker that are made via the service attach a header in the response called &ldquo;x-invalidates&rdquo; that looks something like:</p>

<p><code>
x-invalidates: /jobseekers/123
</code></p>

<p>Varnish, when it sees this header, turns the value into a content expiring regular expression. My team mate <a href="http://twitter.com/johnconnolly">@johnconnolly</a> learned about this general technique from <a href="https://twitter.com/kevburnsjr">Kevin Burns Jr.</a> at <a href="RESTFest">http://restfest.org</a> 2012.  I used Kevin’s post on the <a href="http://blog.kevburnsjr.com/tagged-cache-invalidation">subject</a> as a jumping off point for our implementation.</p>

<h3>Via Magic:</h3>

<p>Once upon a time, we had a database administrator named Gennady. Gennady wrote a <a href="http://www.dinodigusa.com/images/Magic1.gif">PHP script that reads MySQL’s binary logs</a>, looking for changes to a set of predefined tables. When it sees an update, it finds the primary key for the row and fires off an invalidation request. In our case, a purge of the cached jobseeker url in Varnish. This allows us to invalidate cached job seeker entities even when the update was performed via legacy code that interacts directly with the database rather than through the service.</p>

<p>If you were to do this manually, it would look something like:</p>

<p><code>
curl -X PURGE varnish-jobseeker/jobseekers/123
</code></p>

<hr />

<h2>Act IV: Configuration Spelunking</h2>

<p>So, how did we do it? I’m going to break down our configuration into its parts and cover the general role each part plays. From here on out, I’m assuming you understand the basics of how Varnish works and how you configure it. Also, there is some repetition in our configuration that isn’t required, it just makes it easier for our configuration management tool, puppet, to create the final output.</p>

<h3>Load Balancing</h3>

<p>We have four service servers behind varnish so we create four backend entries and then set up a director to round robin between them. Then in vcl_recv, we set our director named &lsquo;nodes&rsquo; to be the backend that we will use to fetch content.</p>

<p>``` bash
backend JS1 {
  .host  = &ldquo;JS1&rdquo;;
  .port  = &ldquo;8080&rdquo;;</p>

<p>  &hellip;
}</p>

<p>backend JS2 {
  .host  = &ldquo;JS2&rdquo;;
  .port  = &ldquo;8080&rdquo;;</p>

<p>  &hellip;
}</p>

<p>backend JS3 {
  .host  = &ldquo;JS3&rdquo;;
  .port  = &ldquo;8080&rdquo;;</p>

<p>  &hellip;
}</p>

<p>backend JS4 {
  .host  = &ldquo;JS4&rdquo;;
  .port  = &ldquo;8080&rdquo;;</p>

<p>  &hellip;
}</p>

<p>director nodes round-robin {
  { .backend = JS1 ; }
  { .backend = JS2 ; }
  { .backend = JS3 ; }
  { .backend = JS4 ; }
}</p>

<p>sub vcl_recv {
  set req.backend = nodes;
}</p>

<h1>store in cache only by url, not backend host</h1>

<p>sub vcl_hash {
  hash_data(req.url);
  return (hash);
}
```</p>

<h3>Degraded</h3>

<p>Each backend is setup with a probe url that we use to check its health. If the probe url doesn&rsquo;t return at least one HTTP 200 response within a fifteen second period, we mark that backend as unhealthy.</p>

<p>``` bash
backend &hellip; {
   &hellip;</p>

<p>  .probe = {</p>

<pre><code>.url = "/donjohnson/pulse";
.interval = 5s;
.timeout = 250ms;
.window = 3;
.threshold = 2;
</code></pre>

<p>  }
}
```</p>

<p>Varnish has the concept of a grace period, wherein, we can keep content alive in our cache past the TTL based on the health status of our backends. In our case, when the all backends are down, we keep cached items alive for an extra hour. During this time, we operate in a degraded status. Read requests for cached items will be handled while write requests will fail because there is no backend service to handle them.</p>

<p>``` bash
sub vcl_fetch {
  # max time to keep an item in the cache past its ttl
  # used in conjunction with code in vcl_recv to
  # deal with &lsquo;sick&rsquo; backends
  set beresp.grace = 1h;</p>

<p>  &hellip;
}</p>

<p>sub vcl_recv {
  &hellip;</p>

<p>  # extra ttl for cached objects based on backend health
  if (!req.backend.healthy) {</p>

<pre><code>set req.grace = 1h;
</code></pre>

<p>  } else {</p>

<pre><code>set req.grace = 15s;
</code></pre>

<p>  }
}
```</p>

<h3>Invalidation</h3>

<p>We do two types of invalidation:</p>

<ul>
<li>invalidation based on the &lsquo;x-invalidates&rsquo; header that comes back with a response</li>
<li>&lsquo;manual&rsquo; invalidation based on sending the HTTP PURGE verb to a url in the Varnish cache.</li>
</ul>


<p>The ability to do a manual purge is limited to a small set of IP addresses that we validate against when a purge request is received.</p>

<p>``` bash
acl purge {
  &ldquo;localhost&rdquo;;
  &ldquo;10.10.10.10&rdquo;;
}</p>

<p>sub vcl_recv {
  &hellip;</p>

<p>  # &lsquo;manual&rsquo; purge
  if (req.request == &ldquo;PURGE&rdquo;) {</p>

<pre><code>if (client.ip ~ purge) {
   return(lookup);
}

error 405 "Not allowed.";
</code></pre>

<p>  }</p>

<p>  &hellip;
}
```</p>

<p>The actual mechanics of doing the purge are fairly simple. If the url attempted to be purged exists, purge it and return a 200.</p>

<p>``` bash
sub vcl_hit {
  # &lsquo;manual&rsquo; purge
  if (req.request == &ldquo;PURGE&rdquo;) {</p>

<pre><code>purge;
error 200 "Purged.";
</code></pre>

<p>  }
}
```</p>

<p>If it doesn&rsquo;t, return a 404 response code:</p>

<p>``` bash
sub vcl_miss {
  # &lsquo;manual&rsquo; purge
  if (req.request == &ldquo;PURGE&rdquo;) {</p>

<pre><code>purge;
error 404 "Not in cache.";
</code></pre>

<p>  }
}
```</p>

<p>Update requests include invalidation-related headers. Every request we fetch has, inside of Varnish, its request url stored in a special x-url header. This will be used as the url to check the x-invalidates header against. As this header is purely for our internal use, we remove it before delivering items to a client:</p>

<p>``` bash
sub vcl_fetch {
  &hellip;</p>

<p>  set beresp.http.x-url = req.url;</p>

<p>  &hellip;
}</p>

<p>sub vcl_deliver {
  # clear internal cache invalidation header before sending to client
  unset resp.http.x-url;
}
```</p>

<p>Any &lsquo;successful&rsquo; PUT, POST, DELETE or PATCH response will have its x-invalidates header used as a regular expression to invalidate existing content whose x-url header matches the x-invalidates regex.</p>

<p>```
sub vcl_fetch {
  &hellip;</p>

<p>  # cache invalidation
  set beresp.http.x-url = req.url;
  if (req.request == &ldquo;PUT&rdquo; || req.request == &ldquo;POST&rdquo; || req.request == &ldquo;DELETE&rdquo; || req.request == &ldquo;PATCH&rdquo;) {</p>

<pre><code>if  (beresp.status &gt;= 200 &amp;&amp; beresp.status &lt; 400) {
 ban("obj.http.x-url ~ " + beresp.http.x-invalidates);
}
</code></pre>

<p>  }
}
```</p>

<hr />

<h2>Act V: The final product</h2>

<p>And finally, we put it all together into a complete file (note, we use Varnish 3, the semantics around ban/purge changed from v2 to v3):</p>

<p>``` bash
backend JS1 {
  .host  = &ldquo;JS1&rdquo;;
  .port  = &ldquo;8080&rdquo;;
  .probe = {</p>

<pre><code>.url = "/donjohnson/pulse";
.interval = 5s;
.timeout = 250ms;
.window = 3;
.threshold = 2;
</code></pre>

<p>  }
}</p>

<p>backend JS2 {
  .host  = &ldquo;JS2&rdquo;;
  .port  = &ldquo;8080&rdquo;;
  .probe = {</p>

<pre><code>.url = "/donjohnson/pulse";
.interval = 5s;
.timeout = 250ms;
.window = 3;
.threshold = 2;
</code></pre>

<p>  }
}</p>

<p>backend JS3 {
  .host  = &ldquo;JS3&rdquo;;
  .port  = &ldquo;8080&rdquo;;
  .probe = {</p>

<pre><code>.url = "/donjohnson/pulse";
.interval = 5s;
.timeout = 250ms;
.window = 3;
.threshold = 2;
</code></pre>

<p>  }
}</p>

<p>backend JS4 {
  .host  = &ldquo;JS4&rdquo;;
  .port  = &ldquo;8080&rdquo;;
  .probe = {</p>

<pre><code>.url = "/donjohnson/pulse";
.interval = 5s;
.timeout = 250ms;
.window = 3;
.threshold = 2;
</code></pre>

<p>  }
}</p>

<p>director nodes round-robin {
  { .backend = JS1 ; }
  { .backend = JS2 ; }
  { .backend = JS3 ; }
  { .backend = JS4 ; }
}</p>

<h1>what machines can institute a &lsquo;manual&rsquo; purge</h1>

<p>acl purge {
  &ldquo;localhost&rdquo;;
  &ldquo;192.1.1.4&rdquo;;
}</p>

<h1>store in cache only by url, not backend host</h1>

<p>sub vcl_hash {
  hash_data(req.url);
  return (hash);
}</p>

<p>sub vcl_fetch {
  # max time to keep an item in the cache past its ttl
  # used in conjunction with code in vcl_recv to
  # deal with &lsquo;sick&rsquo; backends
  set beresp.grace = 1h;</p>

<p>  # cache invalidation
  set beresp.http.x-url = req.url;
  if (req.request == &ldquo;PUT&rdquo; || req.request == &ldquo;POST&rdquo; || req.request == &ldquo;DELETE&rdquo; || req.request == &ldquo;PATCH&rdquo;) {</p>

<pre><code>if  (beresp.status &gt;= 200 &amp;&amp; beresp.status &lt; 400) {
 ban("obj.http.x-url ~ " + beresp.http.x-invalidates);
}
</code></pre>

<p>  }
}</p>

<p>sub vcl_recv {
  set req.backend = nodes;</p>

<p>  # &lsquo;manual&rsquo; purge
  if (req.request == &ldquo;PURGE&rdquo;) {</p>

<pre><code>if (client.ip ~ purge) {
   return(lookup);
}

error 405 "Not allowed.";
</code></pre>

<p>  }</p>

<p>  # extra ttl for cached objects based on backend health
  if (!req.backend.healthy) {</p>

<pre><code>set req.grace = 1h;
</code></pre>

<p>  } else {</p>

<pre><code>set req.grace = 15s;
</code></pre>

<p>  }
}</p>

<p>sub vcl_deliver {
  # clear internal cache invalidation header before sending to client
  unset resp.http.x-url;
}</p>

<p>sub vcl_hit {
  # &lsquo;manual&rsquo; purge
  if (req.request == &ldquo;PURGE&rdquo;) {</p>

<pre><code>purge;
error 200 "Purged.";
</code></pre>

<p>  }
}</p>

<p>sub vcl_miss {
  # &lsquo;manual&rsquo; purge
  if (req.request == &ldquo;PURGE&rdquo;) {</p>

<pre><code>purge;
error 404 "Not in cache.";
</code></pre>

<p>  }
}
```</p>

<h2>Hidden Track Bonus Act:</h2>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/varnish-in-five-acts/varnish-all-the-things.jpg"></p>

<p>Join the discussion over at <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=5651874">Hacker News</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
