<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: How we work | TheLadders Engineering Stories]]></title>
  <link href="http://dev.theladders.com/categories/how-we-work/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://dev.theladders.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-09-30T13:14:51-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://dev.theladders.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[TheLadders Engineering]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Evolution of QA at TheLadders]]></title>
    <link href="http://dev.theladders.com/2013/05/the-evolution-of-qa-at-theladders/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-16T09:04:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://dev.theladders.com/2013/05/the-evolution-of-qa-at-theladders</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><blockquote><p>Change means that what was before wasn&rsquo;t perfect. People want things to be better.</p><footer><strong>&mdash;Esther Dyson</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>Looking back on my 6+ years at TheLadders, I realize how much has changed. When I first joined the company at the start of 2007, there were five other people on the QA team supporting a team of 12 software developers. We followed a strict waterfall process. Product ideas were generated, researched and solidified before any conversation with the development or QA teams. Product managers would spend a large portion of their time hunkered down at their desks writing specification documents, complete with statements on purpose and scope, workflows, wireframes and interaction rules.</p>

<p>After these documents were approved by business owners, the development, QA, and design teams would meet to walk through the document with the goal of estimating the implementation time. QA played the role of a customer advocate and tried to ensure that there was as little uncertainty in the documentation as possible. Instead of walking out of the meeting with estimates, the Product Manager would usually leave with a list of missing workflows and use cases that they would need to add to the spec before development began.</p>

<p>Eventually a release date would be set. Spec and design mocks in hand, the development team would start building the feature.  The QA team would write test cases. We created long lists of actions and expected outcomes that we would use to manually test the development team’s work. Test automation &ndash; unit, integration, functional, load, et al &ndash; was a distant dream. Our primary interaction with the development team was proving the existence of bugs that they couldn’t reproduce.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/the-evolution-of-qa-at-theladders/it-works-on-my-machine.png"></p>

<p>Even though both the development and QA teams worked off of the same documents, the software never matched the expected behavior according to the test case. Preparing for a release was a never-ending cycle of testing, bug-finding, bug-fixing, and retesting. Fixed release dates and not testing until the end of the development cycle led to releases that were huge events with late, stressful nights leading up to release and late, stressful nights spent cleaning up after it was over!</p>

<p>Between major releases, QA was either responding to customer issues, estimating how long it would take to test an upcoming project, or maintaining our set of regression test case documents in Excel.</p>

<h2>Fast forward to 2009.</h2>

<p>The development team had grown to 35. The QA team had shrunk to 4. We’d transitioned to Scrum a few months previous and shuffled the production teams around to form 4 cross-functional ones. Each team consisted of developers, a QA lead, a designer, a copy editor, and a product manager. The move to Scrum was bumpy as we molded the framework into a process that worked for us but teams had started to find a groove. Ideas were generated and defined within each team, we were checking in with each other often, and delivering value to our customers faster. The teams were working like well-oiled machines&hellip; almost.</p>

<p>Selecting user stories to be undertaken during an iteration had become a team decision, however then the Product Manager and QA rep would work together, without the rest of the team, to define the requirements for each story and flesh them out into use case documents. QA still played the role of customer advocate: working to clearly define expected behavior of each user story in terms of the use case document.</p>

<p>The developers would use these documents to build each user story. Sometimes, they&rsquo;d also write unit tests to cover a few of the more important use case scenarios. Before a story was considered &ldquo;done&rdquo;, a code review would need to be completed by at least two developers. In order to make sure that each story met customer expectations, QA would need to manually test the feature. The need for manual testing didn’t end there. At the end of each iteration, QA would run through the entire regression suite before releasing.</p>

<p>We had made some improvements, but it was clear that we could improve the process if we increased communication of requirements and lessened the amount of manual testing that needed to be done.</p>

<p>We were releasing every two weeks. They were smaller and less stressful than in the past. QA still spent a lot of time manually testing, but it was done throughout the iteration instead of being squeezed in at the end. This meant that QA had a lot more downtime than before. While some of this time was spent doing the work we had always done, we also made sure to spend time learning about new tools and best practices. Over time, we learned a lot about automated functional testing. We experimented with different frameworks, starting with a simple record-and-playback tool, until we learned more about what we needed and which tools might best fit that need. I’ll write a post later to shed some light on what that journey was like, but suffice it to say that it took quite a bit of trial and error!</p>

<h2>Fast forward to now.</h2>

<p>We&rsquo;ve moved beyond Scrum to an adapted Agile process that emphasises cross-functional, independent, and highly collaborative teams. Each team is free to adopt practices that work for them. They have free reign to define the way that they work amongst themselves. There are certain commonalities that hold true across all our teams:</p>

<p><strong>QA plays the role of customer advocate</strong>. We know our customers well and our applications even better. This gives us a unique perspective when defining new user stories that helps our teams deliver better products for our users.</p>

<p><strong>The teams define user stories together</strong>. QA still helps flesh out requirements and acceptance criteria, but with the participation of the rest of the team. Defining requirements as a team helps us make sure that we&rsquo;re all on the same page which in turn helps us work better and faster.</p>

<p><strong>We aren&rsquo;t heavy-handed with the documentation</strong>. We&rsquo;ve found that most of our previous attempts at documentation were wasteful &ndash; and often not as useful to the developers as we thought. Instead, after each team conversation around story requirements QA either writes notes and acceptance criteria on the back of the story card (if the team uses a whiteboard to manage their backlog) or in comments attached to the story in Trello.</p>

<p><strong>We automate tests when it&rsquo;s the smart thing to do</strong>. Manually testing everything definitely was not the best thing for us to do, but <a href="http://xkcd.com/1205/">neither is automating every test</a>. Instead, QA and the developers have frequent conversations around how to appropriately test each user scenario: Can it be sufficiently covered in a unit or integration test? Does it make sense to write an expensive automated functional test that checks the functionality through the browser? How important is this functionality? What&rsquo;s the risk of it breaking? We also keep test coverage at the front of our minds and use different <a href="http://dev.theladders.com/2013/02/mutation-testing-with-pit-a-step-beyond-normal-code-coverage/">strategies</a> to make sure that we can trust the tests that we do automate.</p>

<p><strong>Developers write most of our automated tests</strong>. Whether unit, integration, functional, or load tests, usually it&rsquo;s a developer that&rsquo;s going to write it. QA does pitch in when they can but with one QA lead per team, it&rsquo;s not feasible for them to write all of the automated tests without becoming a bottleneck.</p>

<p><strong>We peer review code</strong> with QA actively participating.</p>

<p><strong>We&rsquo;ve set up continuous integration builds</strong>. All of our unit-level tests run after each commit and all of our automated functional regression tests must pass before each deployment. If a test fails, we fix it.</p>

<p>And of course, QA is still responsible for investigating and responding to customer issues. Some things will never change.</p>

<p>We&rsquo;ve come a long way! But that doesn&rsquo;t mean that we can&rsquo;t get better. As a wise man* once said, consistency requires you to be as ignorant today as you were a year ago. Here at TheLadders, we&rsquo;re always learning.</p>

<p>*Bernard Berenson</p>

<p>Join the discussion over at <a href="http://www.softwaretestingclub.com/forum/topics/how-has-the-role-of-qa-evolved">Software Testing Club</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[TheLadders Onboarding: A Retrospective]]></title>
    <link href="http://dev.theladders.com/2013/03/theladders-on-boarding-a-retrospective/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-28T12:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://dev.theladders.com/2013/03/theladders-on-boarding-a-retrospective</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><blockquote><p>Whatever you do or dream you can do – begin it. Boldness has genius and power and magic in it.</p><footer><strong>&mdash;Johann Wolfgang von Goethe</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/dilbert-onboarding.gif" title="&lsquo;Onboarding&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>Just before joining TheLadders, I read a post on their dev blog detailing a new onboarding process for incoming engineers. I was very interested in what I&rsquo;d soon learn about its execution. If you&rsquo;ve not had the chance to read through this post, you can find it <a href="http://dev.theladders.com/2013/02/onboarding/">here</a>.</p>

<p>The onboarding process could be broken into two main sections. The first started when we were given a few user stories and were asked to build a corresponding system while following some fairly restrictive <a href="https://github.com/TheLadders/object-calisthenics#the-rules">guidelines</a>. These restrictions challenged us to reevaluate our normal architecting techniques and develop less-than-obvious solutions to this problem. The rules allowed us to implement our solution in the language of our own choosing, and I chose Ruby. The chance to showcase my skills for the first time at a new company excited me.</p>

<p>The second section spanned the next eight days. We dove into Robert Martin’s SOLID principles video series. After watching, learning, and discussing each one of the the five principles, we proceeded to work on code with real-world <a href="https://github.com/TheLadders/solid-exercises">examples</a> of principle violations. Between these videos and exercises, we met with established engineers at TheLadders to discuss the subject matter and our own philosophies on software craftsmanship.</p>

<p>This was the first time I&rsquo;d ever had a formal onboarding. I&rsquo;ve worked for agencies and other product companies, both larger and smaller, before joining TheLadders. This was brand new. I&rsquo;d encourage every software company to seriously consider a process like this for their new engineers. Why? Here are a few reasons:</p>

<ul>
<li>I was allowed access to the top engineers in the company, learning not only about the way software was written at the TheLadders but also where and how the team was looking to grow.</li>
<li>I was able to get a strong feeling for the culture and technologies used as well as prevailing opinions on languages, practices and history. This was also a great opportunity for engineers at TheLadders to learn more about me and get a good picture of my experience and viewpoints.</li>
<li>It also served as a vacation from production code, deadlines and the stress of the everyday that we encounter wherever we go. We were encouraged to stretch our solutions and see where they took us.</li>
</ul>


<p>You may have heard of Rich Hickey’s <a href="http://blip.tv/clojure/hammock-driven-development-4475586">Hammock Driven Development</a>, the idea that spending time away from your code produces unexpected benefits. In the same vein, I&rsquo;ll call what we did for these two weeks Garbage Driven Development. What do I mean when I say garbage? The code written while practicing GDD is never going into production. It’ll never really do anything beyond providing a learning experience and proving a point you’d like to make. You don’t feel pressure to make sure the code fits within a particular context, that it’s easily readable by others, or that it’ll be maintainable going forward. In the end, the code may be quite eloquent or look like garbage, but it doesn&rsquo;t really matter. Try that idea you’ve always thought about but never had time to implement. Buck best practices to see if you can find better ones. When you’re done, it’s garbage. Developers would be well served to routinely make time to focus less on product and more on process.</p>

<p>Most of all, this process woke me up from the monotony of just pushing out code and inspired me to learn and pursue more of my own side projects. I&rsquo;ve wanted to read more, explore new languages, and try new ways of doing things. It was an excellent way to frame the start of a new chapter in my life as an engineer.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Catechism of Code]]></title>
    <link href="http://dev.theladders.com/2013/02/onboarding/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-01T06:34:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://dev.theladders.com/2013/02/onboarding</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><blockquote><p>&ldquo;Begin, be bold, and venture to be wise.&rdquo;</p><footer><strong>&mdash;Horace</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>All things have a beginning, some cosmologists may disagree, but for our purposes we will assume the universe had a start. How things start sets the tone for how they will continue and ultimately how they will end. So it is with employment at TheLadders.</p>

<p>If you ask the most recent developers to join TheLadders, <a href="http://twitter.com/johnconnolly">@johnconnolly</a> and <a href="http://twitter.com/casio_juarez">@casio_juarez</a>, they probably can point to more than a few bumps in the road. But learn, iterate, repeat. Starting today, we are introducing a new onboarding plan&hellip;</p>

<h2><strong>Day Zero</strong></h2>

<p>Once the usual HR paperwork is out of the way, get this:</p>

<p><img src="/images/floating_flaming_retina_imac_15_inch.JPG" alt="15 inch retina macbook" /></p>

<p>Install your favorite IDE and tools and <a href="https://github.com/SeanTAllen/OS-X-Customizations">make that MacBook your own</a>.</p>

<h2><strong><strong>Day One</strong></strong></h2>

<p>We’ll start you off working on a modified version of the Thoughtworks &ldquo;Object Calisthenics&rdquo; exercise. You can find our version on <a href="https://github.com/TheLadders/object-calisthenics">our github.</a></p>

<p>Why? We&rsquo;ve found that most programmers still have a very procedural mindset when it comes to code. They favor if statements over the use of polymorphic objects, tend towards code that spreads knowledge about domain objects across a wide range of classes (usually a wide range of controllers in most web apps)  and a variety of other potentially problematic tendencies. We originally did the Thoughtworks &ldquo;Object Calisthenics&rdquo; exercise as a team at TheLadders in September of 2012 to start a conversation about a variety of OO techniques that we rarely saw in our existing codebase. Each of the rules that the exercise lays down might seem silly in a production codebase, but they aren&rsquo;t meant as hard and fast rules during day to day work. They are meant to guide the exercise and force you into thinking about coding in a way that you perhaps haven&rsquo;t before. Things like:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>favoring polymorphic objects over conditionals</p></li>
<li><p>observing the law of demeter</p></li>
<li><p>not overloading classes with multiple responsibilities</p></li>
</ul>


<p>These rules are then applied to a kata that introduces new developers to a core part of TheLadders domain: applying to a job, and some of the key concepts: jobs, job seekers, recruiters, and resumes.</p>

<p>Each new developer spends their first day working through the exercise with an existing member of our team. Discussing why you might want to follow a particular rule in production code, why you might not. Pairing through blockages where how to continue without violating the rules of exercise aren&rsquo;t obvious. The overarching idea is to start a conversation about ideas that we think are valuable. The rules and the exercise are just a means to start that conversation in a concrete setting. I&rsquo;m renowned in the office for getting very hand wavey while discussing complicated programming topics and having these conversation while working on code is much more effective.</p>

<p>So great, that&rsquo;s day 1, but we have a full 2 week onboarding so, what else do we do?</p>

<h2><strong>Days Two to Six</strong></h2>

<p>Start watching the SOLID series videos from Clean Coders, doing <a href="https://github.com/TheLadders/solid-exercises">exercises we have designed around them</a> and talking through the issues raised in the videos. Uncle Bob does an excellent job in the series of presenting engineering concepts in a way that firmly expresses that everything is a tradeoff. It has been said that &ldquo;programmers know the value of everything and the tradeoffs of nothing&rdquo;. I&rsquo;ve always taken that to mean that many programmers need black and white rules for what to do and what not to do and have a hard time understanding the tradeoffs involved with a particular practice or design. All best practices need to be broken sometime, all good design patterns eventually become bad ones when put in certain contexts. Uncle Bob&rsquo;s SOLID videos do an excellent job of both presenting the SOLID principles and discussing tradeoffs involved.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s all well and good, but what does this really mean? Let&rsquo;s jump into Day 2 and walk through what we do.</p>

<ol>
<li><p> Start by watching &ldquo;<a href="http://cleancoders.com/codecast/clean-code-episode-9/show">Clean Code Episode 9: The Single Responsibility Principle</a>&rdquo;</p></li>
<li><p> Stop at key points during the episode to discuss salient points</p></li>
<li><p> Talk more in general about the single responsibility principle, why you would want to apply it, etc. at the end</p></li>
<li><p> Crack open some legacy Ladders' code that violates the single responsibility principle for a concrete example of the mess violating it can get you into</p></li>
<li><p> Work together to refactor said code so that it no longer violates the single responsibility principle</p></li>
</ol>


<p>Not bad for Day 2. Hands on exposure to some of hairy areas of our legacy codebase and a chance to talk about the values we hope everyone on the development team shares.</p>

<h2><strong>Day Seven and Beyond</strong></h2>

<p>If you’re doing the math, you might notice that with 5 SOLID episodes that only gets us up to the end of Day 6 and two weeks is ten work days. What do we do with the other 4 days? Good question. We don&rsquo;t know. We&rsquo;ll never know because it will vary from person to person. We expect that over the course of the first six days, we&rsquo;ll see areas that we should address. Perhaps we will go back over some concepts from the object calisthenics exercise that were confusing or problematic. Perhaps a crash course on domain modeling. Perhaps an overview of how we want to use hypermedia to drive our RESTful services. Maybe they need more time with the SOLID exercises. The possibilities are endless and driven by the individual we are seeking to bring on board.</p>

<p>How have you been on-boarded at other companies?  We’d love to hear ideas for improving our own process, and don’t forget <a href="http://careers.theladders.com">we’re hiring</a>, so join TheLadders today and we will work hard to make your transition to our team as smooth as possible.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
